[SPEAKER_01]: Bhante, can you clarify for me what is this cittanimitta?
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems quite an important term to understand the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, clarify it for me, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, think of it as... as we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_00]: For an untrained mind, the attention goes onto something and it's kind of fully absorbed by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if they practice a degree of reflection, they step back from it, what they step back into becomes a new actual thing, which means they remain non-discerning the peripheral, the general, the negative, in regard to that obviously positive thing that's present, be it a feeling, a thought, sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your attention determines if it's going to be actual or there will be a peripheral recognized in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is discerned on the basis of peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start discerning the peripheral on the basis of arisen things, then, eventually, you start recognizing that on that peripheral, that's what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what citta is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm getting back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it's not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, give us this answer and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is to see that feelings and perceptions, all these things, if you were to see the
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously present... well, if you were to feel feelings simultaneously present and perceive perceptions simultaneously with the feelings that are being felt, that will already... that can only be done... that can only be discerned on the basis of mind discerning the peripheral in regards to the actual areas and more particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: Need more.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you don't even know how to feel until you become mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it makes even less sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: I lose it, I lose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for a mind that is not developed in mindfulness, basically, there's just another word you can say for a mind that's not developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That mind, that person, that tujana, he can't even, he can't feel properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't know what feelings are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he doesn't understand what he's feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he doesn't know how to feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we can see that often the way people speak about the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would use the designation that can only be applied to perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if they don't know what, you know, they cannot distinguish between perception and feelings, still they feel and they perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: They feel and they perceive in terms of obviously the aggregates are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean there is no feeling there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they don't know how to feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means they're just fully and always constantly liable to feelings, while its nature remains completely obscured from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha said, my teaching is for the one who feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the one who is sort of touchy-touchy and, you know, hugging trees and sort of universal love.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one who actually recognizes the phenomenon of feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being present.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would see that every feeling, in that sense, if you are mindful, you will see that every feeling basically pertains to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every feeling is cetasika in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every feeling is mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, every feeling becomes almost like... every feeling becomes peripheral, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even... because if you look at the actual feeling which you're feeling, what you're expecting to find in the sphere of actual is that which you perceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you usually start associating feeling with heat in your body or with pain in your elbow or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: They're simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even conceive them apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what a feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, because people have no basis of proper mindfulness, they have no basis of knowing how to feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: How to recognize the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they cannot, in their perception, recognize that there is actually feeling present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Human being is present with that, because that's peripheral in regard to the actual perception they're staring at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you can start to recognize it, then... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which you start to recognize, that's the, basically, beginning, sort of, to discern the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The science of the phenomenon of the mind, which is perception determined upon the presence of... simultaneous presence of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simultaneously present perception, simultaneously present feeling, that experience as a whole is what the sign of the mind... what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, getting the sign of the mind is kind of a precursor to fully becoming established in the phenomenon of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you mean... can it be something like that, you know, you are engaged with some particulars, being aware of this or that, but peripherally you are aware of your... of this...
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh, like that whole concept of the body, we were talking about yesterday, but also that there is a mind present, which is the feeling and perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, no, no, no, that would be an extra, unnecessary, redundant layer.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are mindful of the general, in regard to particular, that experience is the experience of the mind that is mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, so the mind is this mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the mind is revealed by that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me answer her.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me think about her.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind is this peripheral or is the whole thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think, for the practice purpose, you can... it would probably be more helpful to think of it as peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is found in the phenomenon of the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh... anything that is actual has arisen on the basis of the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it... things start to make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind is precursor of all things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... so you realize that what has arisen particularly in your perception is only intelligible and discerned as such because the mind was already there peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, at the same time,
[SPEAKER_00]: If the matter of the particular perception was not there, the mind as the field would have not been defined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, so the body is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because otherwise it would just be mind existing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mind cannot exist on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or consciousness and form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Form and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can say mind and body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not as accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mind and body are peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind and body are peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is peripheral is only in regard to what you're attending to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, body is not always peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's... if that's... if you're attending to a body, then the body is actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, something else is peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a fixed thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's hard to see it, because it's determined by what you attend, not by what you hold to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why holding on to views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you get the right view, it will keep
[SPEAKER_00]: Redirecting you back to the right point.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't have a right view, it takes you completely away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, inevitably, the way we are sort of formed, the five aggregates, you give priority to that view that's being held.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and you can't not hold views, because that becomes another view you hold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, what is, as you said, so what is very fair depends on what you... Attempt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Attempt, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you attend your body, present in this situation, in this room, seated, what's peripheral in regard to that, you can call the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will see then the mind becomes the negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind doesn't appear in that direct sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, say, while you're seated, then you start using your hands, picking up the cup.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now the general body that is present becomes peripheral to this particular engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means now the mind is where that body is, that general body, not the particular one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why... that's why, basically, the mind is inseparable from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the same sense, that's why, if you were to liberate that... that mind, that general mind, from any liability to feelings, wrong views, wrong assumptions, then it becomes infinite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that... that peripheral, this is... this time, just goes...
[SPEAKER_00]: And, for right view, you need to start getting the notions of that peripheral, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cittanimitta is the... is the condition, sort of, for arising of the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's for the same very reason as, like, the previous talk, when I was talking about samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why samādhi develops mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It develops the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The composure of mindfulness results in mind development.
[SPEAKER_00]: The expanding of the recognition of the peripheral in regard to the actual.